<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<appendix label="C" version="5.0" xml:id="working-with-roadmaps"
          xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
          xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink"
          xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
          xmlns:ns5="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml"
          xmlns:ns4="http://www.w3.org/2000/svg"
          xmlns:ns3="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML"
          xmlns:ns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook">
  <title>Working with Roadmaps</title>

  <para>The good news: OpenStack has unprecedented transparency when it comes
  to providing information about what's coming up. The bad news: each release
  moves very quickly. The purpose of this appendix is to highlight some of the
  useful pages to track, and take an educated guess at what is coming up in
  the Icehouse release and perhaps further afield.<indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>Icehouse</primary>

      <secondary>upcoming release of</secondary>
    </indexterm><indexterm class="singular">
      <primary>OpenStack community</primary>

      <secondary>working with roadmaps</secondary>

      <tertiary>release cycle</tertiary>
    </indexterm></para>

  <para>OpenStack follows a six month release cycle, typically releasing in
  April/May and October/November each year. At the start of each cycle, the
  community gathers in a single location for a design summit. At the summit,
  the features for the coming releases are discussed, prioritized, and
  planned. <xref linkend="release-cycle-diagram" /> shows an example release
  cycle, with dates showing milestone releases, code freeze, and string freeze
  dates, along with an example of when the summit occurs. Milestones are
  interim releases within the cycle that are available as packages for
  download and testing. Code freeze is putting a stop to adding new features
  to the release. String freeze is putting a stop to changing any strings
  within the source code.</para>

  <figure xml:id="release-cycle-diagram">
    <title>Release cycle diagram</title>

    <mediaobject>
      <imageobject>
        <imagedata width="6in" fileref="http://git.openstack.org/cgit/openstack/operations-guide/plain/doc/openstack-ops/figures/osog_ac01.png"></imagedata>
      </imageobject>
    </mediaobject>
  </figure>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-information-available">
    <title>Information Available to You</title>

    <para>There are several good sources of information available that you can
    use to track your OpenStack development desires.<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>OpenStack community</primary>

        <secondary>working with roadmaps</secondary>

        <tertiary>information available</tertiary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <para>Release notes are maintained on the OpenStack wiki, and also shown
    here:</para>

    <informaltable cellpadding="2" cellspacing="0" rules="all">
      <thead>
        <tr>
          <th>Series</th>

          <th>Status</th>

          <th>Releases</th>

          <th>Date</th>
        </tr>
      </thead>

      <tbody>
        <tr>
          <td><para>Juno</para></td>

          <td><para>Under
            development</para></td>

          <td><para><link
            xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Icehouse">2014.1</link></para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 17, 2014</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><para>Icehouse</para></td>

          <td><para><link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Icehouse_Release_Schedule">Current stable release, security-supported</link> </para></td>

          <td><para><link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Icehouse">2014.1</link></para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 17, 2014</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td rowspan="2"><para>Havana</para></td>

          <td rowspan="2"><para>Security-supported
          </para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Havana">2013.2</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 4, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2013.2.1">2013.2.1</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Dec 16, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td rowspan="5"><para>Grizzly</para></td>

          <td rowspan="5"><para>EOL</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Grizzly">2013.1</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 4, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2013.1.1">2013.1.1</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>May 9, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2013.1.2">2013.1.2</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Jun 6, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2013.1.3">2013.1.3</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Aug 8, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2013.1.4">2013.1.4</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Oct 17, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td rowspan="5"><para>Folsom</para></td>

          <td rowspan="5"><para>Community-supported</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Folsom">2012.2</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Sep 27, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.2.1">2012.2.1</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Nov 29, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.2.2">2012.2.2</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Dec 13, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.2.3">2012.2.3</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Jan 31, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.2.4">2012.2.4</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 11, 2013</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td rowspan="4"><para>Essex</para></td>

          <td rowspan="4"><para>Community-supported</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Essex">2012.1</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 5, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.1.1">2012.1.1</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Jun 22, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.1.2">2012.1.2</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Aug 10, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2012.1.3">2012.1.3</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Oct 12, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td rowspan="2"><para>Diablo</para></td>

          <td rowspan="2"><para>Deprecated</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Diablo">2011.3</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Sep 22, 2011</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>

          <td><para> <link
          xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/2011.3.1">2011.3.1</link> </para></td>

          <td><para>Jan 19, 2012</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><para>Cactus</para></td>

          <td><para>Deprecated</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Cactus">2011.2</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Apr 15, 2011</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><para>Bexar</para></td>

          <td><para>Deprecated</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Bexar">2011.1</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Feb 3, 2011</para></td>
        </tr>

        <tr>
          <td><para>Austin</para></td>

          <td><para>Deprecated</para></td>

          <td><para> <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/ReleaseNotes/Austin">2010.1</link>
          </para></td>

          <td><para>Oct 21, 2010</para></td>
        </tr>
      </tbody>
    </informaltable>

    <para>Here are some other resources:</para>

    <itemizedlist>
      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="http://status.openstack.org/release/">A breakdown of
        current features under development, with their target
        milestone</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/openstack">A list of all
        features, including those not yet under development</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/Summit/Icehouse/Etherpads">Rough-draft design
        discussions ("etherpads") from the last design summit</link></para>
      </listitem>

      <listitem>
        <para><link xlink:href="https://review.openstack.org/">List of individual
        code changes under review</link></para>
      </listitem>
    </itemizedlist>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-influencing">
    <title>Influencing the Roadmap</title>

    <para>OpenStack truly welcomes your ideas (and contributions) and highly
    values feedback from real-world users of the software. By learning a
    little about the process that drives feature development, you can
    participate and perhaps get the additions you desire.<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>OpenStack community</primary>

        <secondary>working with roadmaps</secondary>

        <tertiary>influencing</tertiary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <para>Feature requests typically start their life in Etherpad, a
    collaborative editing tool, which is used to take coordinating notes at a
    design summit session specific to the feature. This then leads to the
    creation of a blueprint on the Launchpad site for the particular project,
    which is used to describe the feature more formally. Blueprints are then
    approved by project team members, and development can begin.</para>

    <para>Therefore, the fastest way to get your feature request up for
    consideration is to create an Etherpad with your ideas and propose a
    session to the design summit. If the design summit has already passed, you
    may also create a blueprint directly. Read this <link
    xlink:href="http://vmartinezdelacruz.com/how-to-work-with-blueprints-without-losing-your-mind/">blog post about how to work with
    blueprints</link> the perspective of Victoria Martínez, a developer
    intern.</para>

    <para>The roadmap for the next release as it is developed can be seen at
    <link xlink:href="http://status.openstack.org/release/">Releases</link>.</para>

    <para>To determine the potential features going in to future releases, or
    to look at features implemented previously, take a look at the existing
    blueprints such as&#160;<link
    xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/nova">OpenStack Compute (nova)
    Blueprints</link>, <link xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/keystone">OpenStack
    Identity (keystone) Blueprints</link>, and release notes.</para>

    <para>Aside from the direct-to-blueprint pathway, there is another very
    well-regarded mechanism to influence the development roadmap: the user
    survey. Found at <link
    xlink:href="http://openstack.org/user-survey"></link>, it allows you to
    provide details of your deployments and needs, anonymously by default.
    Each cycle, the user committee analyzes the results and produces a report,
    including providing specific information to the technical committee and
    technical leads of the projects.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="aspects-to-watch">
    <title>Aspects to Watch</title>

    <para>You want to keep an eye on the areas improving within OpenStack. The
    best way to "watch" roadmaps for each project is to look at the blueprints
    that are being approved for work on milestone releases. You can also learn
    from PTL webinars that follow the OpenStack summits twice a
    year.<indexterm class="startofrange" xml:id="OSaspect">
        <primary>OpenStack community</primary>

        <secondary>working with roadmaps</secondary>

        <tertiary>aspects to watch</tertiary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <section xml:id="roadmap-driver-improvements">
      <title>Driver Quality Improvements</title>

      <para>A major quality push has occurred across drivers and plug-ins in
      Block Storage, Compute, and Networking. Particularly, developers of
      Compute and Networking drivers that require proprietary or hardware
      products are now required to provide an automated external testing
      system for use during the development process.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="roadmap-easier-upgrades">
      <title>Easier Upgrades</title>

      <para>One of the most requested features since OpenStack began (for
      components other than Object Storage, which tends to "just work"):
      easier upgrades. From Grizzly onward (and significantly improved in
      Havana), internal messaging communication is versioned, meaning services
      can theoretically drop back to backward-compatible behavior. This allows
      you to run later versions of some components, while keeping older
      versions of others.</para>

      <para>In addition, a lot of focus has been placed on database
      migrations. These are now better managed, including the use of the Turbo
      Hipster tool, which tests database migration performance on copies of
      real-world user databases.</para>

      <para>These changes have facilitated the first proper OpenStack upgrade
      guide, found in <xref linkend="ch_ops_upgrades" />, and will continue to
      improve in Icehouse.<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Icehouse</primary>

          <secondary>upgrades in</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="nova-network-deprecation">
      <title>Deprecation of Nova Network</title>

      <para>With the introduction of the full software-defined networking
      stack provided by OpenStack Networking (neutron) in the Folsom release,
      development effort on the initial networking code that remains part of
      the Compute component has gradually lessened. While many still use
      <literal>nova-network</literal> in production, there has been a
      long-term plan to remove the code in favor of the more flexible and
      full-featured OpenStack Networking.<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>nova</primary>

          <secondary>deprecation of</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <para>An attempt was made to deprecate <literal>nova-network</literal>
      during the Havana release, which was aborted due to the lack of
      equivalent functionality (such as the FlatDHCP multi-host
      high-availability mode mentioned in this guide), lack of a migration
      path between versions, insufficient testing, and simplicity when used
      for the more straightforward use cases <literal>nova-network</literal>
      traditionally supported. Though significant effort has been made to
      address these concerns, <literal>nova-network</literal> will not be
      deprecated in the Icehouse release. In addition, the Program Technical
      Lead of the Compute project has indicated that, to a limited degree,
      patches to <literal>nova-network</literal> will now again begin to be
      accepted.<indexterm class="singular">
          <primary>Icehouse</primary>

          <secondary>nova network deprecation</secondary>
        </indexterm></para>

      <para>This leaves you with an important point of decision when designing
      your cloud. OpenStack Networking is robust enough to use with a small
      number of limitations (IPv6 support, performance issues in some
      scenarios) and provides many more features than
      <literal>nova-network</literal>. However, if you do not have the more
      complex use cases that can benefit from fuller software-defined
      networking capabilities, or are uncomfortable with the new concepts
      introduced, <literal>nova-network</literal> may continue to be a viable
      option for the next 12 to 18 months.</para>

      <para>Similarly, if you have an existing cloud and are looking to
      upgrade from <literal>nova-network</literal> to OpenStack Networking,
      you should have the option to delay the upgrade for this period of time.
      However, each release of OpenStack brings significant new innovation,
      and regardless of your use of networking methodology, it is likely best
      to begin planning for an upgrade within a reasonable timeframe of each
      release.</para>

      <para>As mentioned, there's currently no way to cleanly migrate from
      <literal>nova-network</literal> to neutron. We recommend that you keep a
      migration in mind and what that process might involve for when a proper
      migration path is released. If you must upgrade, please be aware that
      both service and instance downtime is likely unavoidable.</para>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-ML2">
    <title>Replacement of Open vSwitch Plug-in with <phrase
    role="keep-together">Modular Layer 2</phrase></title>

    <para>The Modular Layer 2 plug-in is a framework allowing OpenStack
    Networking to simultaneously utilize the variety of layer-2 networking
    technologies found in complex real-world data centers. It currently works
    with the existing Open vSwitch, Linux Bridge, and Hyper-V L2 agents and is
    intended to replace and deprecate the monolithic plug-ins associated with
    those L2 agents.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-nova-v3-api">
    <title>Compute V3 API</title>

    <para>The third version of the Compute API was broadly discussed and
    worked on during the Havana and Icehouse release cycles. Current
    discussions indicate that the V2 API will remain for many releases, but
    this is a great time to evaluate the Compute API and provide comments
    while it is being defined. Of particular note is the decision that the V3
    API will not support XML messages—being JSON only. This was based on the
    poor testing of existing XML responses in the V2 API and the lack of
    effort to continue to develop and maintain an entire second response type.
    Feedback on this and any such change is welcome by responding to the <link
    xlink:href="https://www.openstack.org/user-survey/Login">user survey</link>.<indexterm
        class="singular">
        <primary>Icehouse</primary>

        <secondary>Compute V3 API</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-triple-o">
    <title>OpenStack on OpenStack (TripleO)</title>

    <para>This project continues to improve and you may consider using it for
    greenfield <phrase role="keep-together">deployments</phrase>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-savanna">
    <title>Data Processing (Sahara)</title>

    <para>A much-requested answer to big data problems, a dedicated team has
    been making solid progress on a Hadoop-as-a-Service project.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-baremetal">
    <title>Bare-Metal Deployment (Ironic)</title>

    <para>Though bare-metal deployment has been widely lauded, and development
    continues, the project to replace the Compute bare-metal driver will not
    graduate in Icehouse. A particular blueprint to follow is <link
    xlink:href="https://blueprints.launchpad.net/ironic/+spec/migration-from-nova"> Migration Path from Nova's BM
    Driver</link>, which tracks the ability to move to the new project from an
    existing bare-metal deployment.<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Icehouse</primary>

        <secondary>Compute bare-metal deployment</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-trove">
    <title>Database as a Service (Trove)</title>

    <para>The OpenStack community has had a database-as-a-service tool in
    development for some time, and we will finally see the first integrated
    release of it in Icehouse. Initially, it will only support MySQL, with
    further options available in Juno onward, but it should be able to deploy
    database servers out of the box in a highly available way from this
    release.<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Icehouse</primary>

        <secondary>database-as-a-service tool</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-marconi">
    <title>Messaging as a Service (Marconi)</title>

    <para>A service to provide queues of messages and notifications has
    entered “incubation,” meaning if the upcoming development cycles are
    successful, it will be released in <phrase
    role="keep-together">Juno</phrase>.</para>
  </section>

  <section xml:id="roadmap-scheduling">
    <title>Scheduler Improvements</title>

    <para>Both Compute and Block Storage rely on schedulers to determine where
    to place virtual machines or volumes. In Havana, the Compute scheduler
    underwent significant improvement, while in Icehouse the scheduler in
    Block Storage is slated for a boost. Further down the track, an effort
    started this cycle that aims to create a holistic scheduler covering both
    will come to fruition.<indexterm class="singular">
        <primary>Icehouse</primary>

        <secondary>scheduler improvements</secondary>
      </indexterm></para>

    <section xml:id="roadmap-volumes">
      <title>Block Storage Improvements</title>

      <para>The team discussed many areas of work at the Icehouse summit,
      including volume migration support, Ceph integration, and access control
      for volumes.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="roadmap-python-sdk">
      <title>Toward a Python SDK</title>

      <para>Though many successfully use the various python-*client code as an
      effective SDK for interacting with OpenStack, consistency between the
      projects and documentation availability waxes and wanes. To combat this,
      an <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/PythonOpenStackSDK">effort to improve the
      experience</link> has started. Cross-project development efforts in
      OpenStack have a checkered history, such as the <link
      xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/OpenStackClient"> unified client project</link>
      having several false starts. However, the early signs for the SDK
      project are promising, and we expect to see results during the Juno
      cycle.<indexterm class="endofrange" startref="OSaspect" /></para>
    </section>
  </section>
</appendix>