<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="example_architecture">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Example Architectures</title>
    <para>To understand the possibilities OpenStack offers it's best to start
    with basic architectures that are tried-and-true and have been tested
    in production environments. We offer two such examples with basic pivots on
    the base operating system (Ubuntu and Red Hat Enterprise Linux) and the
    networking architectures. There are other differences between these two
    examples, but you should find the considerations made for the choices in each
    as well as a rationale for why it worked well in a given environment.</para>
    <para>Because OpenStack is highly configurable, with many different
    back-ends and network configuration options, it is difficult to write
    documentation that covers all possible OpenStack deployments. Therefore,
    this guide defines example architectures to simplify the task of
    documenting, as well as to provide the scope for this guide. Both of the
    offered architecture examples are currently running in production and
    serving users.</para>
    <para>As always, refer to the Glossary if you are unclear about any of the
    terminology mentioned in these architectures.</para>
    <xi:include href="section_arch_example-nova.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="section_arch_example-neutron.xml"/>
    <section xml:id="example_archs_conclusion">
        <title>Parting Thoughts on Architectures</title>
        <para>With so many considerations and options available our hope is to
        provide a few clearly-marked and tested paths for your OpenStack
        exploration. If you're looking for additional ideas, check out the
            <link linkend="use-cases"
            >Use Cases</link> appendix, the <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/"
                >OpenStack Installation Guides</link>, or the <link
                    xlink:href="http://openstack.org/user-stories/"
                    >OpenStack User Stories page</link>.</para>
    </section>
</chapter>

