<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter [
        <!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
        <!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
        <!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
        <!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
        <!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
]>
<chapter xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="advanced_configuration">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Advanced Configuration</title>
    <para>OpenStack is intended to work well across a variety of installation
          flavors, from very small private clouds to large public clouds. In
          order to achieve this the developers add configuration options to
          their code which allow the behaviour of the various components to be
          tweaked depending on your needs. Unfortunately it is not possible to
          cover all possible deployments with the default configuration values.</para>

    <para>At the time of writing, OpenStack has over 1,500 configuration options.
          You can see them documented at
          <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/config_overview.html">the OpenStack configuration reference guide</link>. This chapter cannot hope to
          document all of these, but however we do try to introduce the important
          concepts so that you know where to go digging for more information.</para>

    <section xml:id="driver_differences">
    <title>Differences between various drivers</title>
    <para>Many OpenStack projects implement a driver layer, and each of these
          drivers will implement their own configuration options. For example
          in OpenStack Compute (Nova), there are various hypervisor drivers
          implemented -- libvirt, xenserver, hyper-v and vmware for example.
          Not all of these hypervisor drivers have the same features, and each
          has different tuning requirements.</para>

    <note><para>The currently implemented hypervisors are listed on
          <link xlink:href="http://docs.openstack.org/trunk/config-reference/content/section_compute-hypervisors.html">the OpenStack documentation website</link>. You can see a matrix of the
          various features in OpenStack Compute
          (Nova) hypervisor drivers on the OpenStack wiki at
          <link xlink:href="https://wiki.openstack.org/wiki/HypervisorSupportMatrix">the Hypervisor support matrix page</link>.</para></note>

    <para>The point we are trying to make here is that just because an option
          exists doesn't mean that option is relevant to your driver choices.
          Normally the documentation notes which drivers the configuration
          applies to.</para>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="periodic_tasks">
    <title>Periodic tasks</title>
    <para>Another common concept across various OpenStack projects is that of
          periodic tasks. Periodic tasks are much like cron jobs on traditional
          Unix systems, but they are run inside of an OpenStack process. For
          example, when OpenStack Compute (Nova) needs to work out what images
          it can remove from its local cache, it runs a periodic task to do this.</para>

    <para>Periodic tasks are important to understand because of limitations in
          the threading model that OpenStack uses. OpenStack uses cooperative
          threading in python, which means that if something long and
          complicated is running, it will block other tasks inside that process
          from running unless it voluntarily yields execution to another
          cooperative thread.</para>

    <para>A tangible example of this is the nova-compute process. In order to
          manage the image cache with libvirt, nova-compute has a periodic
          process which scans the contents of the image cache. Part of this
          scan is calculating a checksum for each of the images and making sure
          that checksum matches what nova-compute expects it to be. However,
          images can be very large and these checksums can take a long time to
          generate. At one point, before it was reported as a bug and fixed,
          nova-compute would block on this task and stop responding to RPC
          requests. This was visible to users as failure of operations such
          as spawning or deleting instances.</para>

    <para>The take away from this is if you observe an OpenStack process which
          appears to "stop" for a while and then continue to process normally,
          you should check that periodic tasks aren't the problem. One way to
          do this is to disable the periodic tasks by setting their interval to
          zero. Additionally, you can configure how often these periodic tasks
          run -- in some cases it might make sense to run them at a different
          frequency from the default.</para>

    <para>The frequency is defined separately for each periodic task.
          Therefore, to disable every periodic task in OpenStack Compute
          (Nova), you would need to set a number of configuration
          options to zero. The current list of configuration options
          you would need to set to zero are:</para>

                <itemizedlist>
                <listitem><para>bandwidth_poll_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>sync_power_state_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>heal_instance_info_cache_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>host_state_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>image_cache_manager_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>reclaim_instance_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>volume_usage_poll_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>shelved_poll_interval</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>shelved_offload_time</para></listitem>
                <listitem><para>instance_delete_interval</para></listitem>
                </itemizedlist>

    <para>To set a configuration option to zero, include a line such as
          <literal>image_cache_manager_interval=0</literal> to your
          <filename>nova.conf</filename> file.</para>

    <para>This list will change between releases, so please refer to
          your configuration guide for up to date information.</para>

    </section>

    <section xml:id="specific-advanced-config-topics">
    <title>Specific configuration topics</title>
    <para>This section covers specific examples of configuration options you
          might consider tuning. It is by no means an exhaustive list.</para>

        <section xml:id="specific-advance-config-nova">
        <title>OpenStack Compute (Nova)</title>

            <section xml:id="specific-advanced-config-period-tasks">
            <title>Periodic task frequency</title>
            <para>Before the Grizzly release, the frequency of periodic tasks
                  was specified in seconds between runs. This meant that if the
                  periodic task took 30 minutes to run and the frequency was
                  set to hourly, then the periodic task actually ran every 90
                  minutes, because the task would wait an hour after running
                  before running again. This changed in Grizzly, and we now
                  time the frequency of periodic tasks from the start of the
                  work the task does. So, our 30 minute periodic task will run
                  every hour, with a 30 minute wait between the end of the
                  first run and the start of the next.</para>
            </section>
        </section>
    </section>
</chapter>
