<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE part [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">
]>
<part xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="architecture">
    <title>Architecture</title>
    <partintro>
      <para>
        Designing an OpenStack cloud is a great achievement. It requires a
        robust understanding of the requirements and needs of the cloud's
        users to determine the best possible configuration to meet them.
        OpenStack provides a great deal of flexibility to achieve your
        needs, and this part of the book aims to shine light on many of the
        decisions you need to make during the process.
      </para>
      <para>To design, deploy, and configure OpenStack, administrators
        must understand the logical architecture. A diagram can help
        you envision all the integrated services within
        OpenStack and how they interact with each other.</para>
      <para>OpenStack modules are one of the following types:</para>
      <itemizedlist role="compact">
        <listitem>
          <para>Daemon. Runs as a background process. On Linux platforms, a daemon is
            usually installed as a service.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Script. Installs a virtual environment and runs tests.</para>
        </listitem>
        <listitem>
          <para>Command-line interface (CLI). Enables users to submit API
            calls to OpenStack services through commands.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <para>As shown, end users can interact through the dashboard,
        CLIs, and APIs. All services authenticate through a common
        Identity Service and individual services interact with each
        other through public APIs, except where privileged
        administrator commands are necessary. The diagram shows the
        most common, but not the only logical architecture for an
        OpenStack cloud.</para>
      <figure>
        <title>OpenStack Havana Logical Architecture</title>
        <mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata width="6in"
            fileref="figures/osog_0001online.png"/>
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></figure>
    </partintro>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_examples.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_provision.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_cloud_controller.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_compute_nodes.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_scaling.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_storage.xml"/>
    <xi:include href="ch_arch_network_design.xml"/>
</part>
