<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE preface [
<!-- Some useful entities borrowed from HTML -->
<!ENTITY ndash  "&#x2013;">
<!ENTITY mdash  "&#x2014;">
<!ENTITY hellip "&#x2026;">
<!ENTITY plusmn "&#xB1;">


]>
<preface xmlns="http://docbook.org/ns/docbook"
    xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude"
    xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" version="5.0"
    xml:id="section_yk2_jpr_lj">
    <?dbhtml stop-chunking?>
    <title>Preface</title>
    <para>OpenStack is an open source platform that lets you build an
        Infrastructure as a Service (IaaS) cloud that runs on commodity
        hardware.</para>
    <section xml:id="introduction-to-openstack">
        <title>Introduction to OpenStack</title>
        <para>OpenStack believes in open source, open design, open development,
            all in an open community so anyone can participate. The long-term
            vision for OpenStack is to produce a ubiquitous open source cloud
            computing platform that meets the needs of public and private cloud
            providers regardless of size. OpenStack services control large pools
            of compute, storage, and networking resources throughout a data
            center. </para>
        <para>Each service provides a REST API so that all these resources can
            be managed through a dashboard that gives administrators control
            while empowering users to provision resources through a web
            interface, through a command-line client, or through software
            development kits that support the API. Many OpenStack APIs are
            extensible, meaning you can keep compatibility with a core set of
            calls while providing access to more resources and innovating
            through API extensions. The OpenStack project is a global
            collaboration of developers and cloud computing technologists
            producing the open standard cloud computing platform for both public
            and private clouds. The project aims to deliver solutions for all
            types of clouds by being simple to implement, massively scalable,
            and feature-rich. The technology consists of a series of
            interrelated projects delivering various components for a cloud
            infrastructure solution.</para>
        <para>Okay, you say, OpenStack is open source cloud. Are there others?
            Yes, Eucalyptus offers an open source version of their private cloud
            offering that provides services compatible with Amazon Web Services
            (AWS) APIs such as EC2 and S3. With Ubuntu Server 11.10 release,
            OpenStack became supported by default rather than Eucalyptus for
            Ubuntu Server releases. The product targets private cloud deployers
            who want to maintain compatibility with Amazon Web Services by
            partnering with Amazon. Apache CloudStack is another example of an
            open source cloud project, but it only runs on Ubuntu 10.04. It
            offers computing as a core service, with connections to storage
            services. Citrix purchased the project technology for $200 million
            in 2011 when buying cloud.com, then released it to Apache in April
            2012. The API compatibility for CloudStack centers on AWS
            APIs.</para>
        <para>OpenStack is designed for scalability, so you can easily add new
            compute and storage resources to grow your cloud over time.
            Organizations such as HP and Rackspace have built massive public
            clouds on top of OpenStack. OpenStack is more than a software
            package that you run as-is. It lets you integrate a number of
            different technologies to construct a cloud. This approach provides
            great flexibility, but the number of options might be bewildering at
            first.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="who-this-book-is-for"><title>Who This Book Is For</title>
        <para>This guide assumes that you are familiar with the Ubuntu
            distribution of Linux, SQL databases, and virtualization. You
            must be comfortable administering and configuring multiple
            Linux machines for networking. You must install and maintain a
            MySQL database, and occasionally run SQL queries against it.
            </para>
        <para> One of the most complex aspects of an OpenStack cloud is the
            networking configuration. You should be familiar with concepts such
            as DHCP, Linux bridges, VLANs, and iptables. You must also have
            access to a network hardware expert who can configure the switches
            and routers required in your OpenStack cloud.</para>
        <para>This book is for those of you starting to run OpenStack
            clouds as well as those of you who were handed a running one and
            want to keep it running well. Perhaps you're on a devops team,
            perhaps you are a system administrator starting to dabble in the
            cloud, or maybe you want to get on that OpenStack cloud team at your
            company. This book is for all of you.</para></section>
    <section xml:id="how-this-book-is-organized">
        <title>How This Book Is Organized</title>
        <para>This book is organized in two parts, the architecture decisions
            for designing OpenStack clouds and the repeated operations for
            running OpenStack clouds.</para>
        <para>Chapter 1: Provisioning and Deployment: While this book doesn't
            describe installation, we do recommend automation for deployment and
            configuration, discussed in this chapter.</para>
        <para>Chapter 2: Cloud Controller Design: The cloud controller is an
            invention for the sake of consolidating and describing which
            services run on which nodes. The chapter discusses hardware and
            network considerations as well as how to design the cloud controller
            for performance and separation of services.</para>
        <para>Chapter 3: Scaling: This chapter discusses the growth of your
            cloud resources through scaling and segregation
            considerations.</para>
        <para>Chapter 4: Compute Nodes: This chapter describes the compute
            nodes, which are dedicated to run virtual machines. Some hardware
            choices come into play here as well as logging and networking
            descriptions.</para>
        <para>Chapter 5: Storage Decisions: Along with other architecture
            decisions, storage concepts within OpenStack take a lot of
            consideration, and this chapter lays out the choices for you.</para>
        <para>Chapter 6: Network Design: Your OpenStack cloud networking needs
            to fit into your existing networks while also enabling the best
            design for your users and administrators, and this chapter gives you
            in-depth information about networking decisions.</para>
        <para>Chapter 7:  Example Architecture: Because of all the decisions the
            previous chapters discuss, this chapter describes the decisions made
            for this particular book and much of the justification for the
            example architecture.</para>
        <para>Chapter 8: Lay of the Land: This chapter is written to let you get
            your hands wrapped around your OpenStack cloud through command line
            tools and understanding what is already set up in your cloud.</para>
        <para>Chapter 9: Managing Projects and Users: This chapter walks through
            those user-enabling processes that all admins must face to manage
            users, give them quotas to parcel out resources, and so on.</para>
        <para>Chapter 10: User-facing Operations: This chapter moves along to
            show you how to use OpenStack cloud resources and train your users
            as well. </para>
        <para>Chapter 11: Maintenance, Failures, and Debugging: This chapter
            goes into the common failures the authors have seen while running
            clouds in production, including troubleshooting.</para>
        <para>Chapter 12: Network Troubleshooting: Because network
            troubleshooting is especially difficult with virtual resources, this
            chapter is chock-full of helpful tips and tricks to tracing network
            traffic, finding the root cause of networking failures, and
            debugging related services like DHCP and DNS.</para>
        <para>Chapter 13: Logging and Monitoring: This chapter shows you where
            OpenStack places logs and how to best to read and manage logs for
            monitoring purposes. </para>
        <para>Chapter 14: Backup and Recovery: This chapter describes what you
            need to back up within OpenStack as well as best practices for
            recovering backups. </para>
        <para>Chapter 15: Customize: When you need to get a specialized feature
            into OpenStack, this chapter describes how to use DevStack to write
            custom middleware or a custom scheduler to rebalance your
            resources.</para>
        <para>Chapter 16: Upstream OpenStack: Because OpenStack is so, well,
            open, this chapter is dedicated to helping you navigate the
            community and find out where you can help and where you can get
            help.</para>
        <para>Chapter 17: Advanced Configuration: Much of OpenStack is
            driver-oriented, where you can plug in different solutions to the
            base set of services. This chapter describes some advanced
            configuration topics.</para>
        <para>Appendix A: Use Cases: You can read a small selection of use cases
            from the OpenStack community with some technical detail and further
            resources.</para>
        <para>Appendix B: Tales From the Cryp^H^H^H^H Cloud: These are shared
            legendary tales of image disappearances, VM massacres, and crazy
            troubleshooting techniques to share those hard-learned lessons and
            wisdom.</para>
        <para>Appendix C: Resources: So many OpenStack resources are available
            online due to the fast-moving nature of the project, but there are
            also listed resources the authors found helpful while learning
            themselves.</para>
        <para>Glossary: A list of terms used in this book is included, which is
            a subset of the larger OpenStack Glossary available online.</para>
    </section>
    <section xml:id="why-and-how-we-wrote-this-book">
        <title>Why and How We Wrote This Book</title>
        <para>We wrote this book because we have deployed and maintained
            OpenStack clouds for at least a year, and wanted to be able to
            distribute this knowledge to others. After months of being the point
            people for an OpenStack cloud, we also wanted to have a document to
            hand to our system administrators so they'd know how to operate the
            cloud on a daily basis — both reactively and proactively. We wanted
            to provide more detailed technical information about the decisions
            that deployers make along the way.</para>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <para>We wrote this book to help you:<itemizedlist role="compact">
                <listitem>
                    <para>Design and create an architecture for your first
                        non-trivial OpenStack cloud. After you read this guide,
                        you'll know which questions to ask and how to organize
                        your compute, networking, storage resources, and the
                        associated software packages. </para>
                </listitem>
                <listitem>
                    <para>Perform the day-to-day tasks required to administer a
                        cloud.</para>
                </listitem>
            </itemizedlist></para>
        <para>We wrote this book in a Book Sprint, which is a facilitated rapid
            development production method for books. For more information see
            the <link xlink:href="http://www.booksprints.net">Book Sprint
                site</link>. Your authors cobbled this book together in five
            days during February 2013, fueled by caffeine and the best take-out
            food that Austin, Texas could offer. </para>
        <para>On the first day we filled white boards with colorful sticky notes
            to start to shape this nebulous book about how to architect and
            operate clouds. <informalfigure>
                <mediaobject>
                    <imageobject>
                        <imagedata width="5in" fileref="figures/1-IMG_4895.JPG"
                        />
                    </imageobject>
                </mediaobject>
            </informalfigure></para>
        <para>We wrote furiously from our own experiences and bounced ideas
            between each other. At regular intervals we reviewed the shape and
            organization of the book and further molded it, leading to what you
            see today.</para>
        <?hard-pagebreak?>
        <para>The team includes:</para>
        <itemizedlist role="compact">
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Tom Fifield</emphasis>. After
                    learning about scalability in computing from particle
                    physics experiments like ATLAS at the LHC, Tom worked on
                    OpenStack clouds in production to support the Australian
                    public research sector. Tom currently serves as an OpenStack
                    community manager and works on OpenStack documentation in
                    his spare time.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Diane Fleming</emphasis>. Diane
                    works on the OpenStack API documentation tirelessly. She
                    helped out wherever she could on this project.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Anne Gentle</emphasis>. Anne is the
                    documentation coordinator for OpenStack and also served as
                    an individual contributor to the Google Doc Summit in 2011,
                    working with the Open Street Maps team. Anne has worked on
                    doc sprints in the past with FLOSS Manuals’ Adam Hyde
                    facilitating. Anne lives in Austin, Texas.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Lorin Hochstein</emphasis>. An
                    academic turned software developer-slash-operator, Lorin
                    currently works as the Lead Architect for Cloud Services at
                    Nimbis Services where he deploys OpenStack for technical
                    computing applications. He has been working with OpenStack
                    since the Cactus release. Previously, he worked on
                    high-performance computing extensions for OpenStack at
                    University of Southern California's Information Sciences
                    Institute (USC-ISI).</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Adam Hyde</emphasis>. Adam
                    facilitated this Book Sprint. He also founded the Book
                    Sprint methodology and is the most experienced Book Sprint
                    facilitator around. See
                        <uri>http://www.booksprints.net/</uri> for more
                    information. Adam founded FLOSS Manuals—a community of some
                    3,000 individuals developing Free Manuals about Free
                    Software. He is also the founder and project manager for
                    Booktype, an open source project for writing, editing, and
                    publishing books online and in print.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Jonathan Proulx</emphasis>. Jon has
                    been piloting an OpenStack cloud as a senior technical
                    architect at the MIT Computer Science and Artificial
                    Intelligence Lab for his researchers to have as much
                    computing power as they need. He started contributing to
                    OpenStack documentation and reviewing the documentation so
                    that he could accelerate his learning.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Everett Toews</emphasis>. Everett is
                    a Developer Advocate at Rackspace making OpenStack and the
                    Rackspace Cloud easy to use. Sometimes developer, sometimes
                    advocate, and sometimes operator. He's built web
                    applications, taught workshops, given presentations around
                    the world, and deployed OpenStack for production use by
                    academia and business.</para>
            </listitem>
            <listitem>
                <para><emphasis role="bold">Joe Topjian</emphasis>. Joe has
                    designed and deployed several clouds at Cybera, where, as a
                    non-profit, they are building e-infrastructure to support
                    entrepreneurs and local researchers in Alberta, Canada. He
                    also actively maintains and operates these clouds as a
                    systems architect, and his experiences have generated a
                    wealth of troubleshooting skills for cloud
                    environments.</para>
            </listitem>
        </itemizedlist>
    </section>

    <section xml:id="how-to-contribute-to-ops-guide">
        <title>How to Contribute to This Book</title>
        <para>The genesis of this book was an in-person event, but now that the
            book is in your hands we want you to contribute to it. OpenStack
            documentation follows the coding principles of iterative work, with
            bug logging, investigating, and fixing. We also store the source
            content on Github and invite collaborators through the OpenStack
            Gerrit installation, which offers reviews. For the O'Reilly edition
            of this book, we are using their Atlas system which also stores
            source content on Github and enables collaboration among
            contributors.</para>
        <para>Learn more about how to contribute to the OpenStack docs
            at <link
                xlink:href="http://wiki.openstack.org/Documentation/HowTo"
                >Documentation How To</link>
            (http://wiki.openstack.org/Documentation/HowTo).</para>
        <para>If you find a bug and can't fix it or aren't sure it's
            really a doc bug, log a bug at <link
                xlink:href="http://bugs.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals"
                >OpenStack Manuals</link>
            (http://bugs.launchpad.net/openstack-manuals). Tag the bug
            under <guilabel>Extra</guilabel> options with
                <literal>ops-guide</literal> tag to indicate that the
            bug is in this guide. You can assign the bug to yourself
            if you know how to fix it. Also, a member of the OpenStack
            doc-core team can triage the doc bug. </para>
    </section>

</preface>
